welcome everybody this is daniel
and welcome to another uh grandmaster
versus beginner video
uh the first one was very well received
so i'm
you know i've heard everyone's demands
and i'm making another one so
just to recap what i'll be doing in this
video is playing a 15 minute chess game
against
a player in the beginner to intermediate
rating range i won't
i don't know who i'll be playing yet uh
i'll be commentating the game live and
the extended time control
will give me an opportunity to really
talk through my moves to explain
all aspects of my thinking process after
the game we'll do a quick summary
and hopefully everyone whether beginner
or advanced will be able to learn
something so
without further ado i'm going to enter
the pool
and seek a game now just to remind you
the time control will be 15 minutes
per player plus a 10 second increment
which means that 10 seconds are added to
uh my clock and my opponent's clock
after each executed move and we actually
have a very strong player we have an
1800 so
um you know this is a very very uh very
very reasonable opponent
uh this is going to be quite interesting
so he has played
the uh nimsovich larsen opening one b3
what i have done in return
as one is supposed to is occupied the
center
knight f3 attacks my pawn on e5 so i'm
actually going to push it forward this
is a theoretical line
goes 95 this is a theoretical line
uh that is very legitimate um and it's a
very very complicated
type of position where essentially white
is trying to
lure my pawns forward in order to be
able to attack them later
which is something that's kind of called
a hyper modern opening now what i'm
gonna do here
is i'm not going to take this knight i'm
actually going to chase it away with my
queen
it might seem like i'm pinning myself
but in reality because that bishop was
vulnerable
his knight had to escape specifically to
c4 and i'm going to reposition my queen
to g6
my opponent playing very very fast here
something that hopefully i'll make him
regret he keeps moving the same piece
multiple times in the opening and
there's no reason to get intimidated by
anybody who violates opening principles
you simply need to obey them on your own
he goes g3 now i think the problem with
what with what my opponent is doing and
the way to punish him is
you know precisely to obey to the letter
opening principles now what haven't i
done yet i haven't completed my
development
i also haven't occupied the center fully
with my pawns which is what i'm going to
do
here i'm going to go d5 and i'm going to
build a very nice
central pawn chain he goes bishop g2 now
you know all that is left is for me to
develop my pieces what i'm going to do
first
is develop my bishop to e6 to buttress
that e5 pawn
no that is not what i mentioned that was
a bad area he castles
now let's think here this is an
important moment i think this is an
instructive moment
on the one hand i want to either develop
my bishop
or even castle long on the other hand
what i'm realizing here folks
is that my opponent has essentially
abandoned his queen side development
and i think that despite the fact that
i'm not fully developed myself
i think that i'm actually ready to begin
attacking him so
i think i'm going to go h5 to try to
open up that h file
he's played h4 now i've softened him up
a little bit here
and now i can continue developing so now
i'm going to castle long
and this pawn on g3 mark my words
i'm thinking of potential sacrifices he
goes a4
wow so very creative play
definitely not objectively sound and
once again in order to refute this it's
important not to panic
it's important to complete one's
development and then only sacrifice or
start attacking when you're ready to do
so he goes king h2
which wow continuing to play very
quickly i'm
speechless and i think i'm gonna try to
go for something cool here
now what am i thinking about doing i'm
thinking about giving him a nice little
check on g4
but then he can take my knight so i'd
like to give this check on g4
except i don't well if i give this check
on before and he takes with my knight on
second thought
i can then take with the pawn opening up
that age file
and that's exactly what i wanted so i'm
actually going to do that and if you
notice i'm actually threatening to take
his pawn he's got to drop his king back
to g1 i think that's the only
serious move he's got he doesn't do that
he allows me to take on h4 with
check now do i want to rush with that i
can actually
go bishop e5 first getting that bishop
out of you know the sticky spot that it
said now we take on h4
and now we're gonna go for a nice
beautiful little finale he's definitely
this is caught him by surprise
and he has already resigned the game so
you know on the one hand i want to play
another one on the other hand i think
that this was actually a very
instructive game so
i am going to make hopefully an
instructive moment out of this this is
what happens
ladies and gentlemen when you violate
shamelessly opening principles you just
can't do that
now why did he resign here after king g1
i think that i have a very nice way to
finish this game
and that is by playing queen h6 simply
sacrificing the rook now it doesn't take
very long to see
that despite the fact that i've sacked a
rook black's got
absolutely overwhelming pressure on the
king side i'm threatening checkmate
his only way to stave the checkmate off
is to go rookie one
but now after something like g3 all of
my pieces are pouring in
for example takes takes you know let's
say he goes e3
first of all i can take the rook and you
know uh winning the rook back i can also
go bishop g4 i mean
i'd welcome you to you can dig around
this position yourself to see the
abundance of
mating ideas that black has here but
there's no doubt in my mind this is
completely crushing
um and so for that reason he resigned if
he doesn't take my rook
and he goes something like b4 one very
elegant win is to actually
send that rook to h1 in order to make
the bishop vulnerable i'm threatening to
capture it with checkmate
and after bishop g2 well of course this
is
also checkmate so for that reason my
opponent resigned which was very
sensible
now one thing to point out here is that
the the opening that my opponent played
is actually not a bad opening now 95 is
inaccurate
knight d4 is a better move and the
reason you play knight d4 is that
the knight can be supported with e3 but
it's very important to point out that um
when you're not a very advanced player
or you're not very experienced
um it's very very difficult to play in
this kind of style now this is something
that
very strong players can actually get
away with you can violate opening
principles
strategically and still get a decent
position that's what modern chess is all
about
but my recommendation to any of the
viewers who are thinking about playing
offbeat openings
is to first get comfortable playing
sensible classical openings in order to
get
your head around opening principles and
only when you feel very very comfortable
with opening principles
developing your pieces occupying the
center can you start deviating a little
bit
and experimenting now in this position i
think d4 would have been interesting at
least
making a claim in the center my opponent
instead goes knight c4
i position my queen on this very very
nice g6 square
and after knight e3 another mistake my
opponent should have definitely started
concerning himself with developing his
pieces maybe e3 maybe d3
instead he's moving his pieces around
i'm occupying the center developing and
now i go h5
softening him up and like i said this
pawn actually cost him the game
so had he allowed h4 well the opening of
the h file would have just been a
disaster for white
so he went h4 i contin notice that i
don't do anything
drastic i didn't play d4 here i just
continued to develop my pieces until
everything was in the game and only now
do i launch
sort of the decisive invasion again i
think that in this position d3 was
absolutely called for and this was maybe
the last chance for white to at least
have
a fighting shot in the game but after
king h2 i noticed that
the king walked right into this pin
which means that this g3 pawn is
actually not defending h4
had he stepped back with his king i
probably actually would have
sacrificed anyway and then gone queen h6
queen takes h4 so
this is just so overwhelming notice that
i also was patient here i didn't take on
h4 immediately
because well i didn't want this tension
to bother me i played bishop e5 first
attacking the rook
and only after he defended it did i take
on h4 and here he resigned so
a very one-sided game i think my
opponent played too quickly he played
too creatively
but hopefully an instructive game
nonetheless and hopefully a game that
serves as a cautionary warning to
a lot of you who experiment with offbeat
openings
it is absolutely crucial first and
foremost to adhere to solid opening
principles to develop your pieces
without that you're gonna have a debacle
just like my opponent had
in this game thank you and um i'll see
you in the next video hopefully the next
game that i play
uh will be a bit longer but nonetheless
i hope that you enjoyed
and uh feel free to comments and uh
feel free to discuss this game as well
as any other interesting games in the
comments
below thank you very much and i'll see
you in the next video